Inventory of the Klaus Kirchner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Soviet Central Series, 1941-1945; 1-5 (Box 1-5:)
  - So oder So /DEUTSCHE SOLDATEN!..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1407)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1. Description: [This way or that way? You hope to be relieved. But for you there will be no relief... For you there will be only lice, dirt, waiting to be wounded or for a wooden cross with a steel helmet on top...]. Photomontage: A German soldier is holding a safe conduct over his head and demonstrating to his comrades the alternative "This way or that way."
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 179, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1408)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 179... A Japanese newspaper on the military power of the Soviet Union... German soldiers are revolting against the continuation of the war against Russia...]. Photograph: Production site of an American tank factory producing tanks for the Soviet Union.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 155, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1409)
    16x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 155... Germany is governed by plutocrats... German soldiers against the war...]. Drawing by Frans Masareel: [English bombers destroy systematically German armament factories.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 186, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1410)
    17x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 186... Offensive of the Red Army in the area of Kharkov... The Red Army is supplied with weapons and ammunition]. Photograph: [German aircraft shot down by Russians.]
  - DEUTSCHE SOLDATEN! Sorgt dafür, dass dieser Brief aus der russischen..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1412)
    16x18 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1. Description: [German soldiers take care to send this letter to its destination...]. Facsimile of letter mentioned.
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 37, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1415)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 37... The Russian people fight for a just cause... The Russian doctor healed my wounds...]. Photograph: German POWs in their camp.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 180, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1416)
    17x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 180... The fascist leaders are afraid.. In England new Canadian troops are arriving... The main Russian forces are enfolding only just now...]. Photograph: [A new batch of American tanks are arriving on the Eastern front.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 187, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1417)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 187... Destructive blows of the Russians in the area of Kharkov... The spring will help the operations of the partisans]. Photograph: [A group of German soldiers is surrendering.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 188, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1423)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 188... Defeat of the Germans in the area of Kharkov... Uninterrupted flow of English-American weapons to Russia...]. Photograph: [New American tanks have arrived in Russia.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. l56, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1424)
    16x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 156... Hitler's reserves on men are dwindling... Strikes in German factories...]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: [Nieder mit Hitler! Nieder mit dem Krieg.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 181, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1425)
    17x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 181... Beginning of a gigantic offensive of the Russian armies... France - a boiling kettle...]. Photograph: [New American cannon used for arming Russian reserves.]
  - DEUTSCHE SOLDATEN!, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1429)
    Code 1429 contains 8 leaflets made up similarly: [German soldiers!...], followed by a slogan. On reverse a Stalin quote from his order No. 55 and a bilingual safe conduct are added.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 182, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1431)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 182... All the world over the news of the success of the Red Army is being reported... Additional money for the US armament industry... The help of the USA for Russia and England is increasing every month...]. Photograph: [A new delivery of American tanks is arriving at the Eastern front.]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 38, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1433)
    17x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 38... How the POWs are working...]. Two drawings, probably by Heinrich Vogeler and a poem.
  - Gebt Euch furchtlos gefangen!, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1434)
    16x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: A new slogan in phonetic transcription on how to surrender is being given on the leaflet: ["Russ, sdaius!" i.e. "Russian, I surrender!"]. Photograph: A friendly Red Army soldier is inviting Germans to desert without fear.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 189, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1438)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 189... Successful offensive of the Red Army in the area of Kharkov... 'We should not have started this war against Russia...]. Photograph: [Russian booty taken by the Russians.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 190, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1439)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 190... Special information by the Soviet bureau of information. New victories of the Red Army...]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: German soldier is surrendering.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 183, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1440)
    17x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 183... Hitler will break down in the very near future... Anti-German manifestations in France... Severe unrest in Belgium...]. Drawing of partisans, burning houses: [They fight against foreign invaders.]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 39, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1441)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 39... Berliners speak to Berliners... A German POW is buying Russian war loans...]. Photograph: A Russian commissar is speaking friendly with a German POW
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 157, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1442)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 157... A German newspaper is conceding lies... Sabotage in German factories...]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: [Nieder mit Hitler! Nieder mit dem Krieg.]
  - AN ALLE PANZERSCHÜTZEN DER DEUTSCHEN ARMEE..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1443)
    14x19 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [To all members of the mechanized infantry of the German army... Again Guderian and the other producers of corpses force you to fight...]
  - Rettet Eure Lieben vor einem frühzeitigen Tod..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1455)
    12x15 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [Save your loved ones from an early death... Thousands of your comrades have been informed their child, wife, sister, mother or father had died. The war is the cause for their death...]. Photomontage: [...Your children whom you have left at home are in danger...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 191, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1456)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 191... Hitler fascists are withdrawing to the West... 455 German aircraft have been destroyed...]. Photograph: [Germans are laying down their weapons.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 158, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1457)
    17x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 158... Germany will be a land of widows and orphans... The SS and Gestapo are the worst enemies of the German people...]. Two drawings by Erich Weinert: [Another widow - Another orphan.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 184, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1458)
    16x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 184... The Germans have suffered a heavy defeat in the area of Kharkov... New American troops arrived in England...]. Photograph: [An American tank factory producing for the Soviet Union.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 185, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1459)
    16x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 185... The Russians have superior weapons... America is sending new troops to England...]. Photograph: [A group of German soldiers is surrendering.]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 40, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1460)
    16x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 40... German mechanized infantry soldiers are warning their comrades... Soldiers speak to soldiers...]. Photograph, poem: [German POWs are expressing their thoughts on this poster.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 159, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1461)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 159... Hitler's bankers and plutocrats are feeding on German soldiers... German soldiers in the rear areas refuse to go to the front...]. Drawing: [Goering, the last reserves of fat.]
  - MIT JEDEM TAG WÄCHST DIE..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1462)
    14x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [With every day the help the USA and England are giving is growing...]. Photograph: [English tanks for the Soviet Union.]
  - IM JAHRE 1942 wird die ausgeleierte Kriegsmaschine Hitlers zum Teufel gehen..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1463)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [In the year 1942 Hitler's worn war machine will go to the devil...]. Drawing: [Hitler's case in the East is lost...]
  - WER WEITERKÄMPFT WIRD VERNICHTET. Wer sich gefangen gibt..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1464)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [He who continues to fight will be annihilated...]. Drawing: [A Red Army soldier is inviting Germans to desert...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 192, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1465)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 192... Russian attacks in the area of Kharkov... Courageous attacks of Russian partisans in the rear of the Germans...]. Photograph: [Germans are surrendering to Russians.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 193, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1473)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: green or red - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 193... Germans are suffering great losses... 105 German aircraft destroyed...]. Photograph: [Russian bombers ready to start.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 194, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1474)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 194... What Goebbels wrote about this division... And what the soldiers wrote about the same division...]. Photomontage: [You are the next one.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 186, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1475)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 186... England is preparing to land its troops on the Continent... America is increasing its armament production... Dissent between Hitler and Mussolini...]. Cartoon: [Hitler's case is lost...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 160, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1476)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 160... Goering is threatening the German women workers... Wives of soldiers are forced to work...]. Drawing by Frans Masareel: [English bombers destroy systematically German armament factories.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 195, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1482)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 195... The Germans are fleeing and leave their weapons behind... Russian victory in a big tank battle... Instead of relief - death!...]. Drawing: Hitler is bringing death notes to the families of soldiers. [Hitler is caring for the families of dead soldiers.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 196, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1483)
    17x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 196... Terrible, unforgettable moments... No hope ever to leave this hell]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: German soldiers are reading Stalin's order No. 55.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 187, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1484)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 187... Declaration of Balfour, the English Deputy Minister for Air War ... In the USA 40 ships have been built...]. Photograph: [American tank factory producing for the Soviet Union.]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 41, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1485)
    16x20 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 41... Assembly of German POWs in camp No. 74... The Russians treat us well...]. Photograph: A barber shop for German POWs. Poem by Erich Weinert, pseudonym "Tom der Reimer": [Greetings to Goebbels...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 161, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1486)
    16x20 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 161... Hitler fired Darré, the minister for farming... The bony hand of hunger is choking Germany... Despair among German people... German soldiers! Hitler condemned you to death, your families are condemned to suffering...]. Drawing: [Again, mother brought nothing to eat.]
  - WAS HAT STALIN GESAGT? Deutscher Soldat!..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1487)
    15x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [What did Stalin say? In his order of May first he described the German fascists... Hitler and his clique...]. Drawing: [The chain dogs of the German Capitalists.]
  - SCHAUT EUCH NACH DEM RICHTIGEN PLATZ UM... Deutsche Soldaten! Steht Ihr am..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1492)
    15x23 cm - 15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Drawing and poem by Erich Weinert: [German soldiers are reading Stalin's order No. 55...]
  - HITLER RÜSTET ZU EINEM ZWEITEN WINTERFELDZUG..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1493)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler is preparing a second winter campaign... German soldiers! Did you hear that?...]. Hitler caricature: [My soldiers! I took every precaution, you will not miss anything during the coming winter. Hitler in his speech in the Reichstag on 26th April, 1942...]. Poem, author unknown.
  - Die russische Gefangenschaft... Eure Heimkehr..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1494)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1. See also leaflet code 1407, different reverse - description: [This way or that way. Your homecoming is the demand of your people at home... When surrendering - Hands up, and nobody will shoot at you!...]. Photomontage: A German soldier is holding a safe conduct over his head and demonstrating to his comrades the alternative "This way or that way."
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 188, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1496)
    16x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 188... Colossal increase of American shipbuilding... Dissent among Hitler's followers]. Hitler caricature: The Allies will defeat Hitler fascism.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 189, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1497)
    16x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 189... Dark clouds are hanging over Germany... The American fleet was enlarged by 1085 ships]. Caricature: [Hitler is pushing the German people in an abyss.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 162, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1498)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 162... The wives of soldiers are demanding to end this war... Four million fighters against Hitler]. Drawing: [Down with Hitler! Down with the war!]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 190, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1502)
    15x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 190... The Hitler fascists are afraid of the Russian artillery and air force... The war of the partisans in Greece is expanding...]. Photograph: Motorized units of the American Army.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 198, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1504)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 198... Tank battles are being won by the Russians...]. Hitler caricature: [Hitler is pushing the German soldier into an abyss.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 163, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1505)
    16x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 163... Anti-war newspapers are being disseminated in Germany... Anti-war demonstration in Munich...]. Caricature: [Hitler is not Germany.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 191, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1512)
    17x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 191... Hitler's fate will be decided in 1942... Russian weapon superiority...]. Hitler caricature: [Hitler's fate is decided...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 199, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1513)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 199... The Germans suffer enormous losses during their counter attacks... In ten days 543 German airplanes destroyed... Spring victories of the partisans...]. Drawing: [Partisans fight against the foreign invaders.]
  - Hitler hat den Krieg begonnen..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1515)
    13x19 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler started the war. The German people have to end the war by toppling Hitler... Wilhelm Pieck, Wilhelm Florin, Walter Ulbricht, Gustav Sobottka.]
  - Genug der Blutopfer für die deutschen..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1516)
    13x19 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Enough bloodshed for the German plutocrats... Wilhelm Pieck, Wilhelm Florin, Walter Ulbricht, Gustav Sobottka.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 200, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1519)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 200... The German 10th infantry division destroyed... 2100 German soldiers and officers have been cut down by Russian cavalry...]. Photograph: [Russian cavalry is attacking.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 165, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1520)
    16x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 165... Nazi officials do not allow relatives of wounded soldiers to visit them... Mass arrests in German cities...]. Drawing: [Down with the war!]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 192, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1521)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 192... General von Bock is predicting the unavoidable defeat of the Germans... Attempt on the life of Heydrich...]. Photograph: [Mass production of airplanes in the USA.]
  - An die Kameraden der Panzerwaffe!..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1522)
    14x17 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [To the comrades of the tank units... All this is Hitler's fault...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 201, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1523)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 201... The German counter attacks are being repulsed... Slaughter house: 190 corpses per hour...]. Photograph: [A group of German soldiers is surrendering to the Russians.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 166, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1525)
    16x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 166... It has become a fact, the German people are against Hitler... The Nazis intend to hide the truth about what is happening in Germany...]. Drawing: Your families want to have you back.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 193, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1526)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 193... England and the USA accumulate reserves the world has not seen before... In England new Canadian troops have arrived... The French people continue their war against Hitler...]. Photograph: [American airborne troops on their way to their destination...]
  - Merk Dir gut, wie Du Dich vor dem unvermeidlichen Tod retten kannst!..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1531)
    15x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Remember well, how you can save yourself from your unavoidable death... A smart soldier will always find a way to save his life. Don't wait...]
  - Die Pläne des OKW wiederum gescheitert..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1533)
    12x15 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [The plans of the OKW again in vain...]. Photograph: A group of German soldiers taken prisoners in the area of Kharkov:
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 167, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1535)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 167... The Red Army forced the German plutocrats to take off their masks... Anti-war committees of German workers...]. Photomontage: [The German plutocrats are driving German soldiers to a bloody slaughter to increase their profits.]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 202, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1536)
    17x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 202... The plans of the German command have been frustrated... The Germans have lost near Kharkov 90,000 soldiers, officers...]. Photograph: [A group of German soldiers is surrendering to the Russians.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 194, 1942 May (Folder 3: 1537)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 194... American troops will also land in France... Cologne and Essen destroyed]. Photograph: [The English battle ship "Nelson"...]
  - KÖLN UND ESSEN ZERSTÖRT In der Nacht zum 31. Mai bombardierten..., 1942 May (Folder 3: 1541)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Cologne and Essen destroyed. In the night of 31st May, 1250 English heavy bombers destroyed important war objects in Cologne... German soldier!... Remember!... You will lose everything: your life, your home, and your family...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 195, 1942 June (Folder 3: 1542)
    17x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 195... Hitler will be destroyed in this year... 1250 English bombers over Cologne]. Caricature: [Hitler's case is lost...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 168, 1942 June (Folder 3: 1543)
    16x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 168... 1250 bombers over Cologne... Hitler's henchmen kill war veterans...]. Caricature: [Hitler's case is lost]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 203, 1942 June (Folder 3: 1544)
    16x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the - Front No. 203 ... An air attack never seen in history before... losses of Germans in the last week of May...]. Hitler caricature: [1942 Hitler's war machine will be destroyed.]